We're talking about corporate stocks this time.
We've talked already about them a little bit.
We talked about how people
would set up a corporation and
then divide it up into shares.
And then the company grows, and more shares are issued,
and some people sell their shares.
It's a way of creating an organization that works.
We talked about the first
real corporation with traded shares.
That was the Dutch East
India Company in the early 1602.
It was an idea that took
hold and became a scheme for
organization of business and has become extremely important
around the world.
I actually had my own personal experience.
I've created two corporations in my life.
First time, it was one of
my students here at Yale, Alan
Weiss.
Actually, he was not an undergraduate.
He was getting an MBA from the School of Management.
But he came to me after
he graduated and said, I see that
you create home price indexes.
I'd like to start a company and sell them.
And so he went on.
And so he wanted me to advise the company.
And then we decided to make it a corporation.
We brought in my colleague
Chip Case, who's at Wellesley College.
And it's called Case-Shiller Weiss, Incorporated.
And we brought in a fourth, a real businessman.
But he said, it would be ridiculous
to have four names on the company.
So he generously allowed his name, as Chuck Longfield.
But then we set up the company.
And I remember saying, well,
I'm going to start a company.
And he said, well, I'm going to start a company.
And I said, well, I'm
not going to be that involved.
I'll be somewhat involved.
But I'm going to keep teaching at Yale.
And I can't do more than a day
a week at most, or less than that.
So we had to decide how many shares we got.
The only guy who gave it money was the businessman.
So he actually, that's how you do it.
He put money into the company.
The rest of us just agreed to put in time.
So the question is, how
do we divide up the company?
Who gets how many shares?
The businessman put in money.
I'm putting in time.
How do we do that?
And I know I'm not going to put in
as much time as Alan Weiss, who's actually running
the company.
But you know what we did?
We just divided it four ways.
And we set it up.
And it's not a big company, but I'm
saying it's because it's my own personal experience,
having done this.
We sold it.
That was 1991.
We sold it in 2002 to Fiserv, Inc.
And at that time, we had 12 employees.
Never got that big.
But then later on, S&P bought the indexes.
We have the home price indexes called
the S&P K. Shiller Indexes, which now they're
quoted a lot.
But it was a success.
It didn't get really big, but it was a success.
One thing that I learned from
this experience is an appreciation for lawyers.
Because I had never phoned a company before.
I didn't know what kind of things would happen.
It was just all – incidentally, in dividing
up the company, I think it was just fairness.
We thought, we'll all make our
own contribution in our own way.
We can't decide who's more important.
But honestly, I didn't really care about the money.
For me, it was just a new experience.
It was kind of like, we could all be
in this together, if we're all trying to make money
and making something big.
So, it was just kind of a story for
me that made it a little bit of an adventure.
I was in it for the fun of it,
because I really don't feel like I need any money.
I have a job.
I don't aspire to a mansion or anything like that.
But we just did it.
It was fun.
The reason why I appreciated lawyers is that
they seem to anticipate all of our conflicts.
And they wrote things.
We had a corporate charter, a long document.
But it actually made sense.
Because we did get into some conflicts.
This is what happens in a company.
Somebody isn't working as hard as somebody else.
And then some resentment develops.
So what do you do?
The salve is more shares.
If one guy is doing more than another,
it gets brought up at the board meeting, and
someone says, well, let's give this guy more.
It's called a bonus, right?
So we kind of discovered the wisdom of this system.
And it's a great thing.
It's a great thing.
And I think a lot of
people around the world have discovered it.
And that's why corporations are such
an important component of our economy.
So that's just my own personal story.
But I wanted to talk about
big and important corporations, not mine.
But first, I wanted to give you
some sense of perspective on how important corporations
are.
So, let's start with the big one.
So, what is a corporation?
A corporation is a corporate
stock, as traded on stock markets.
So I have data here from the World Bank.
And that's the website.
You can get all the countries of
the world from it, if you want.
And the latest data they have is 2008.
And for various countries of the world here,
they have, or various regions of the world,
they have the value of the stock market.
And the value of the stock market, of
the listed stocks in those countries, in trillions
of U.S. dollars.
And they also have, that's this column, the
trillions of dollars, they also have a fraction
of GDP represented by the stock markets in that country.
So you can see that the biggest stock
market in the world is the United States.
So it's 11.6%.
Okay.
So, that's the biggest.
And the second biggest is the Euro area, 5 trillion.
And UK is very big, because the United
Kingdom was very early to become a financial center.
And it's enormous financial center now.
The interesting thing, though, is as a fraction of GDP.
And you also are confused by when you
talk about fraction of GDP, because it's one year's
GDP we're talking about.
We're comparing a stock with a flow, a
stock of wealth in the stock market, dividing that
by one year's GDP.
So, it shows here that the United States'
stock market in 2008 was worth almost a year's
GDP.
And it was higher than any
other, at least other major country.
Again.
So, it's a symbol of capitalism.
All the value.
If you want to invest in stocks anywhere
you live in the world, they're going to probably
come to the United States, because it's much
higher than, I mean, you could do Asia, Asia
and the Pacific, 3 trillion.
But U.S. is almost four times as large.
That's because of the long history.
This is a capitalist country.
And as I was saying.
The New York corporate law of
1811 kind of got this ball rolling.
And so, it has led the world on that.
But I think if we look at this chart again
in 10 or 20 years, it's going to look different.
Because stock markets are growing around the
world as a form of organization for enterprise.
So, these numbers are, on the rest
of the world, are all going up.
And we'll see.
We'll see.
I think this is going to
be more and more value elsewhere.
I think this is, and
the reason is because it works.
The system coordinates the activity of, it
allows people to work together, and it allows
them to avoid conflicts and motivate
people to work and get things done.
And it creates wealth in people like that.
And so, it seems like something that was learned.
I think it's important to understand that.
I think the reason why we're doing
this, we're doing this for the people.
We're doing this for the people.
We had a big, grand experiment with
socialism, obviously, in many places of the world.
And the socialists kind of gave up on it.
They decided, this works better.
That's why we have in China now market socialism.
Still socialism in a sense.
Maybe it's transformed and it's different.
But it does have a stock market.
And it's growing rapidly there.
But I don't want to
exaggerate the importance of these either.
Because the total value here for the United
States is only 82% of one year's GDP.
Another way of putting it is,
let's round that to 12 trillion.
And there were about 300 million Americans in 2008.
That's $40,000 per capita is the
total value of the stock market.
Now, does that sound like
a lot of money to you?
Well, think of it this way.
If you're a family of four, that's $160,000.
That won't buy you a house.
So it's not that big.
It's big, but it's not that big.
What you have to remember is that corporate
stocks are claims on the profits of corporations.
But most of what corporations do is
take money in and pay it out.
They pay it out to their employees
and to other people, bondholders and taxes.
Right?
And that's what they do.
Lots of other places the money goes to.
So, the actual value of the stock market,
I think most people exaggerate it in their mind.
It's not that big.
It's big, but not that big.
And it's smaller in other countries.
You might wonder, why is it that
in Europe, it's only 38% of GDP?
That sounds funny, right?
I mean, in Europe, they tend to do things.
I don't know.
They're just doing their own thing.
They're moving, I think, in the direction
of more modern corporations, with big exchange-traded corporations.
But they often do things on a smaller scale still.
So, for example, in Germany, you notice that often companies
in Germany, after the end of their name, they have AG.
That stands for Aktiengesellschaft, and
it means stock market company.
But others have GmbH.
Do I have that capitalized right?
Gesellschaft mit beschränkter Haftung.
That means a family company, or it's a
company that's not traded on the stock exchange.
What we're looking at here are traded stocks.
All right.
Actually, my company that I was
just telling you about was never traded.
So, that's called private equity.
If it's on the stock exchange, it's public equity.
And if it's not traded, then it's private.
So, this is private, and this is public.
And there are similar distinctions in
other countries, but this is Germany.
I just wanted to be clear about
one thing, which is the word equity.
It has many different meanings.
It's not just about the stock exchange.
It's about the company.
It's about the companies.
But the meaning that we have
here is shares in a corporation.
I was curious about how far back that term goes.
That word equity, referring to shares, was not
coined until I think it was 1904, according
to the Oxford English Dictionary.
So, and it was American.
It's an American term.
It's now spread over the world.
But we use equity.
I'm trying to think, why do we call it equity?
I'm trying to think.
I think equity means equality and fairness.
And so, what it means is, each share is equal.
I think that's what it means.
We're treating people with equality.
So that's what we have.
We have an equitable division of
profits among owners of a corporation.
By the way, I was making the comparison.
I said the value of shares in
the United States is 40,000 per capita.
And it must be much less in
Europe, like 20,000 or less of traded stocks.
I just want to compare that with houses.
I said 160,000 would be the share of a family
of four in that value of the U.S. stock market.
Actually, it is quite clear that the value
of houses in the United States is equal to
the value of the stock market.
It's greater than the value of the stock market.
According to the Federal Reserve, the total value
of houses in the United States in 2010
was 18 trillion.
That's quite a bit higher than
the value of the stock market.
Incidentally, the Federal Reserve estimates the
total assets of households in the United
States.
And in 2010, that was 69 trillion.
So people own a lot of other things besides stocks.
So I'm kind of minimizing the importance
of the topic of my lecture, because stocks
aren't that valuable.
We couldn't solve the poverty problem by
redistributing the stocks among all the people.
Suppose we did that, all right?
Suppose we said, let's grab all of the
stocks away from the wealthy people, and let's
just share them equally among the whole population.
That's what we're doing.
We're not just sharing them with the whole people.
So some poor family would get $160,000.
One time only, right?
Remember, one time only.
It's a stock.
It's not a per year amount.
So you know, would that lift them out of poverty?
Not if you have to live
the rest of your life on $160,000.
You'd still be in poverty.
So the solution to poverty is not redistributing stocks.
I think the solution to poverty is
instead making these markets work better, so that
we produce more.
OK, so I'm going to talk about stocks
and the different kinds of stocks and the laws
of the stock market here today.
And then I'm going to come at the
end with a couple of examples of companies.
I have an example of Xerox and
Microsoft, both high-flying companies in their days.
So, let's see.
So, another term that I just want to use, corporation.
Corporation comes from the Latin corpus, meaning body.
And the idea of a
corporation is like a legal person.
Every person, every lawyer would say, natural person.
Each one of you is a corporation.
So, corporation is a natural person.
But there are artificial persons as well.
And the corporation is called an artificial
person, even though it really only is owned
by people.
It's like a slave belonging to the shareholders.
So, that's the origin of the term.
Actually, corporations go back to ancient
Rome, where they were called publicani.
And they had a stock market in the Roman Forum.
But they were never allowed to proliferate.
The laws encouraging them did not
create a swell of new companies.
There were very, very few of them.
It wasn't until the 19th
century that corporations really became important.
Now, a corporation is a corporation.
It's a corporation.
It's owned by the shareholders.
And in most corporations, all the shareholders are equal.
That's why we call it equity.
And they all have one vote.
It's one share, one vote.
Not always.
There have been exceptions.
There are non-voting shares.
But usually, they all vote.
And the idea is that the shareholders
vote to elect a board of directors.
This is what they call shareholder democracy.
It's inspired by political democracy.
They're going to set up a company that's democratic.
But it's not democratic in that
every person has a right to vote.
It's each share has a right to vote.
And so, that's the essential idea.
The board of directors, by tradition, when you
form a company in the United States, you
have to choose a state to incorporate.
That's the idea.
And then, each state has its own corporate laws.
So my company, we did it in Massachusetts.
A lot of people like to do it in
Delaware, because they like those laws of Delaware and
the taxes of that state.
And then, the state will dictate some basic rules.
Typically, that you have to have
an annual shareholders meeting where you vote.
That's the idea.
And we did that.
I remember, we followed the law.
It was a great, you know,
someone had a plan, and it worked.
And so, what do you do at the shareholders meeting?
Well, anything according to the bylaws of
the company, certain things have to be decided
there, but not many.
The basic thing you do is,
you hire a chief executive officer.
You agree to hire that person.
And then, the chief executive officer.
And then, the chief executive officer reports to
the board, as an employee of the company.
Okay.
And in the U.S., the chief executive officer
has, by tradition, often been named as chairman
of the board.
But in Europe, that's less likely.
There's some different traditions.
And in the rest of the world, a lot of
people say, it's not good to have the CEO as chairman
of the board.
And the board of directors are
not generally working at the company.
The board of directors are people who were
brought together to give wisdom to the company.
This is what happens.
You're setting up a company, and you don't
know where to go and what to do.
You need someone to run the company.
That's the CEO.
And the CEO is probably a gung-ho guy who's
going to work 80 hours a week, and he's ready
to go.
And he's going to be a great influence.
And so, you get people with different perspectives,
someone who ran a business years ago and is
retired, or any number of different kinds of people.
And the board will meet
more regularly than the shareholders.
Shareholders don't want to get involved,
typically, because they typically own many companies.
They don't have time to worry about.
But you keep a board.
You keep it small enough, so there's not
too many people, like six to ten people.
And they know everything about the company.
They're privy to all the information.
And they talk to each other at regular
meetings, and they call each other up on weekends.
And it's part of the concept of a
director, that you just take responsibility for this company.
You don't run it, but you're responsible for it.
And then the law says, in the United States, that if you
join a board of directors, you're going to be responsible for it.
So, you're going to be responsible for it.
And that's what the board of directors do.
You have a duty of loyalty to the shareholders.
That you were elected by the
shareholders to be on the board.
And those are, you have a duty.
You may not own any shares in the company.
Typically, you don't.
And the board of directors is typically paid only, a
member of the board is paid some token amount of money.
Okay.
You wonder why people do it.
They often do it just to kind
of stay involved and keep themselves learning.
But they can make substantial money.
But they're not the owners of the company.
They don't get rich by it.
They're the kind of wise people that were brought in.
To just, you know, this is your, you joined
the board, it's your, you're taking on a responsibility.
You're not taking on a massive responsibility.
You know, you only meet, you know,
a minimum maybe of four times a year.
And you'll be on phone calls.
But you have some responsibility for the company.
And some people like that.
And they kind of sense that,
well, I'm a productive part of society.
I have this company.
I'll learn all about it and
think about it in a broader perspective.
And so, that seems to work, this
sort of organization seems to work really well.
And you know what will happen?
The board will be talking informally.
And they'll say, is this
CEO really doing a good job?
You know, and they think about it.
I want to just sort
of ask around with our customers.
What do they think?
And so, someone might say, you know,
we could just get a new CEO.
Let's do it.
And then the guy is out immediately,
if they vote at the board meeting.
And this is a structure that keeps companies really good.
And one of the previous questions.
I think it was in the last semester, I
had Carl Icahn come, who is a notorious board breaker.
Well, he comes in.
He told our class here that he likes to buy
enough shares in a company to get himself on the board.
And he loves to go
and show up at board meetings.
He buys companies where
there's relatively ineffective boards.
And the board is not really paying attention.
They're kind of lazy.
And he comes in and he makes
shocking statements like, fire the CEO right now.
This guy is a loser.
And the board gets all upset
because they kind of like the guy.
It's cozy.
But Icahn says, you know, I can do it.
I go in there and I lay it all out.
And maybe take a few meetings.
I can bring them around
and get the company straightened out.
So, this is shareholder democracy, how it works well.
And not everyone agrees with Carl Icahn's interpretation.
He's a controversial guy.
Now, another thing I want to say,
there are basically two kinds of corporations.
There's for-profit and non-profit.
I've been talking about for-profit.
And all these people listed as owning, all
these people listed, I had on the screen,
as listed shares, are for-profit.
That means they have shareholders.
There's another kind of
corporation, which is called non-profit.
And we're standing in one right now.
It's called Yale University.
It's a non-profit corporation.
And it has a board of directors.
They call it the corporation.
They meet regularly.
It's like other corporations.
But there are no shareholders.
So, how can that be?
Who owns Yale?
Well, it's a person.
Yale University, like other universities, is a legal person.
And its rights are defined by law.
And the profits go back to Yale and accumulate there
and are spent for a cause, namely education and research.
So, the board of directors of Yale,
has a different purpose.
They don't have any duty of loyalty
to shareholders, because there are no shareholders.
I mean, we could call you shareholders, I guess,
if you're students here, but that's not what you're called.
And you don't have any rights to the profits.
Profits are spent for good causes.
So, you kind of wonder, well,
those two sound very different, don't they?
Because a for-profit is trying to make money,
and the nonprofit is doing something
for a cause that seems totally different.
But they're not always totally different, because
a lot of what happens in corporations
is determined by kind of
the sociology of the organizational structure.
So, if you have a board of directors,
you know, some people serve on multiple boards.
They'll be on Yale University,
and they'll be on some other company for profit.
But they probably,
the same person, they probably behave
kind of similarly in both places.
So, oddly enough, for-profit and
nonprofit don't often mean that much.
We're going to come back
to nonprofits later in this semester.
But I'm really talking about for-profit.
Now, that sounds kind of selfish, right?
In a sense.
I kind of like non, well,
a lot of us like nonprofits better.
They have a different cachet in our society.
I was talking to Peter Tofano,
who's a professor at Harvard Business School,
who set up a nonprofit company called Doorways to Dreams.
That's the name of his company.
There's a website, search on Doorways to Dreams.
And it's all about finance for the poor,
and the less represented people.
And he said, setting up a nonprofit
was the greatest thing he ever did,
because,
because he,
it opens doors for him.
He walks in and says, I'm running a
nonprofit to benefit poor people in the United States,
getting their financial things in order.
He said, everyone respects me.
And, you know, if I say
I'm trying to make a profit,
they're skeptical.
We have one professor in our econ department, Dean Carlin,
who set up a big nonprofit.
He said,
He,
I mean, we have one of our big Asian universities,
at Yale.
But, it's kind of rare.
Anyway, I'm talking here today about,
this is called, Innovations for Poverty Action.
And just last night,
I had a door to door,
it's my surprise,
I had a young,
Yale freshman come by,
asking me to donate,
here in New Haven.
There's no donations to,
I guess Yale gets donations,
don't get donations, generally.
All right, the value of a
share in the company is equal
to the total value of
the company divided by the number
of shares.
OK, so the market cap of
a company is equal to the value
per share times the number of shares.
Market cap is short for market capitalization.
And that is the value of the company.
So, the key thing you have
to know about a company is, how
many shares are there?
And how many shares do I have?
Maybe I'm repeating myself.
But if there's a million shares outstanding, and I own
1,000 shares.
Then I own 1,000th of everything the company owns.
Because I own after their debt.
But if there's 10 million shares, and I own 1,000
shares, then I own only 1,000th.
You have to know the number of shares.
The number of shares that
you own is meaningless, unless you
know the total number of shares in the company.
And all the different shares are treated equally.
If they pay out any money
to one shareholder, they've got to
pay it out to all
the other shareholders in proportion to
the number of shares.
Now, companies issue dividends.
A dividend is paid to shareholders when the Board of
Directors decides to do it.
And the Board of Directors doesn't have to do it.
I'm talking now exclusively.
So, at a board meeting, they
can say, hey, let's pay a
dividend.
I remember this, because we had exactly this meeting, our
little company.
We gave shares to all
of our employees to motivate them.
Everyone's a shareholder.
But they had tiny numbers.
Some of them had very little shares.
And we had a board meeting,
and we said, we've never paid
a dividend.
Should we do it?
Should we pay a dividend?
And then we had a discussion.
And someone said, well, you know, all these employees
wonder if their shares are worth anything.
So maybe if they got a
check in the mail, they'd feel
better.
But you see, the dividend
is subject to the discretion of
the company.
Ultimately, people own shares to get dividends, right?
Because the dividends is the distribution of profits.
If a company is going to
pay a dividend, it's going to pay
dividends.
If a company never distributed
dividends, it would be like a
nonprofit, right?
If they kept all the profits, they can do that.
There's no law saying that
they have to distribute dividends.
They can just keep it
in the company, and like Yale
University, get a huge endowment and just let it get
bigger and bigger.
But the whole purpose of
a for-profit company is to pay
dividends.
Sooner or later, they do it.
But the big problem is, the for-profit companies don't pay
dividends.
Why not?
Because everybody knows that our money is in the future.
We're starting up.
We're not making a lot of money.
In the future, we'll have a lot of money.
So let's pay dividends later.
For example, Microsoft, that I'm going to describe, went
through decades without ever paying a dividend.
They just kept plowing it back into the company.
Now, if you knew that
they would never pay a dividend,
then you wouldn't want to own Microsoft shares.
You'd think, well, eventually they're going to.
And so, that's why you own the company.
But this is a very common misunderstanding.
A lot of people think that
you buy stocks because the price
will go up.
Well, the price will go
up only because people think there
are more dividends coming.
At least in theory, that's the way it should be.
The price ought to be,
we'll question this later, but it
ought to be the present value of expected future dividends.
So, the true value of
a company is entirely in the
dividends.
It seems a little funny, because you think, well, the
board of directors doesn't have to pay a dividend.
And they could just get
nasty and never pay it out.
But remember, you elect the board of directors.
And so, if you're frustrated that our company is
accumulating lots of money and it's
not paying it out, I want
the money, right?
So, I'm not going to vote for this board.
I'll put Carl Icahn on or someone else.
Pay it out.
And then that's what happens.
They start paying it out.
When they pay out a
dividend, the share price falls generally,
right?
Very simple.
Why would the share price fall
when they pay out a dividend?
Well, because the company is worth less.
They had this money and they paid it out.
So, it should fall by
the amount they paid out divided
by the number of shares, right?
And companies do that routinely.
When they declare a dividend, the price falls.
It's called the ex-dividend.
It's called the ex-dividend price.
And they show it in newspaper.
Well, they don't do it in
– they used to show it in
newspapers.
Now, it would be on the website.
They put a little x by the
stock price on the day after a
dividend is paid to tell you
that the price decline that you
just saw is not anything to worry about.
It doesn't mean there's bad news about the company.
It just means they just paid a dividend.
So, the price routinely goes
down by the amount of the
dividend.
It doesn't mean anything.
Some stockbrokers have tried to alarm investors about
dividend payment dates and mislead them.
And some stockbrokers would say, why don't you buy the
stock right now, because if you
buy it right now, you'll get a
dividend.
They're going to pay a dividend in three days.
Hurry up and buy it, and you'll get the dividend.
That's called selling dividends,
and it's considered unethical
for a broker ever to tell
you that, because it's not a good
thing.
It's not a good thing to do that.
Because it really doesn't matter.
Because if you buy it
later, you won't get the dividend,
but you'll get the share cheaper.
And it all comes out to about the same.
So, you don't have to worry about dividend payment dates,
because the stock price jumps down right after a dividend.
So, it doesn't matter with
you, except maybe if some second
order effects, it doesn't matter with you by a dividend
or a share.
It doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter if you're going
to buy it before or after
a dividend.
All right, so you see the idea here.
The idea of a corporation is,
we have these shares, and the
shares are always saleable.
So, let's say four of us
young people form a company, and then
after a couple of years, one of
us says, I get another job, I'm
tired of this, I want out.
And you say, fine, we'll buy your shares back.
OK?
And you think, OK, we'll sell you shares.
And you think, OK, fair and easy.
So, people can get in and out as they see.
And the only people involved
are people who want to be
involved.
And then you find some new person.
The four of us set up a company.
There's some new guy who just heard of us.
And you think, this is a great idea.
I want in.
So, then you say, all right,
we'll sell you shares in the
company.
But maybe the price has changed, right?
When we started, we might
have been worth a lot less.
But now, we're going to
be in at a new price.
And the price is changing every day.
It makes very good sense.
So, moreover, if the company needs
to raise money to go to
business.
So, we've started a company, and
we need to build a new
factory, let's say, to expand our operations.
Well, we can go out and
issue more shares to buy the factory.
So, we go to a stockbroker
who, it's like a real estate broker
who deals in markets for shares.
And I'm talking about a small
company, so I'm thinking of a
private company, for which there is no stock market price.
But the stockbroker can go out
and say, I'll find a buyer.
I have various contacts.
I know people who deal with individuals, wealthy
individuals, who are looking around for an investment.
Maybe this person will buy some
shares, and then you'll get the
money.
That's an alternative.
That's called equity financing.
So, equity financing is financing by debt.
Your company could also go to
a bank and ask for a loan,
called a corporate loan.
Or your company could borrow
money on the bond market by
issuing bonds.
You can go to a broker and
say, we want to sell corporate bonds.
But the difference of those is
that it's at a fixed interest
rate, and it's not a share in the profits.
So, equity financing tends to attract
investors who take risks.
See, if a company gets debt,
then the debt leverages up the
risk of the company.
Because you, as a shareholder,
now are paid only after the
debtors are paid.
You own the value of
the company, which is the assets
minus the liabilities, as a shareholder.
But you've got to subtract off the liabilities.
So, companies have a choice of
how to, how to get the money
out of their bank, how to finance their operations.
Typically, they start out with equity.
I guess they could start out with debt as well.
But in our case, of our
little company, it was all equity at
first.
Then we got bank loans.
And so, we started to get leveraged.
And that's what happens.
Big companies do the same thing.
I like to talk about the
simple company that you might set up
with your friends, because it seems so personal.
And you can imagine doing that, right?
And you can imagine the
kind of conflicts that would happen.
But these little companies have
a way of growing really, really
big.
So, I'm going to talk about
a little company set up by Bill
Gates and Paul Allen in 1975.
Bill Gates was an undergraduate at Harvard.
And he saw an opportunity, and he dropped out.
He was right.
He never got his Harvard degree.
And he said, I suggest that
if you see such an opportunity,
you do the same thing.
I hate to say it, but
if you can see an opportunity like
that.
So, it started out just
Bill and Paul and their little
company.
But they have a way to
grow into bigger and bigger things.
The question is, are they really different later?
Do they?
So, one important question is about whether big companies
are still functioning in the way I'm describing.
So, I set the idea of a
company up as a structure that lawyers
invented that allow people to
work together and allow them to
get in and out of the company.
Does it really still work
that way for really big companies?
And there's been a complaint
about the stock market that the
companies generally don't issue any more shares once they're
big.
This is the first time I've heard that.
I don't know.
I'm not saying it's a big deal.
I'm just saying that there are some companies that complain,
not saying it's right.
And that the stock market ends
up as a market for existing
shares.
And the idea is, is the
stock market, or are the stock markets
of the world functioning to make capitalism work better?
Well, I could say, well, they
should be, because the price of
a share in a company is
an indicator of the value of the
company, and it directs resources.
I mean, people look at that
price, and they decide where to
invest.
But if they're not issuing
any more shares, does it matter?
So, I had a quote from Karl Marx here.
You've heard of Karl Marx, the founder of communism.
And he, in his book
Capital, Das Kapital, his classic work,
said, I'm quoting Marx.
That was Marx's view.
But even in communist countries,
that view doesn't seem to be
holding sway anymore.
The thing that lent some credibility to Marx's work, was
his book, Capitalism.
credibility to these theories is that it often seems that
big companies don't issue many shares anymore.
And I'm going to qualify that.
But there was a very influential article written by
Stuart Meyers, who is a professor of finance at MIT.
And that was in the Journal of Finance, 1984.
And he gave some statistics.
This was an influential article, making it sound like
shares don't really matter for big companies.
He said, well, how do companies really finance
their needs?
And he gave some statistics.
And he said, well, how do companies really finance their
needs?
And he gave data.
This is Meyers' data from 1973 to 1982.
And he found that 62% of corporate financing needs came
from, in the United States, retained earnings.
What he's saying is, companies, they didn't sell
new shares.
They didn't accumulate profits.
And when they had to build
a new factory, they went to their
own piggy bank, and they bought the new factory, or
whatever it was they needed.
And only 6% was equity-issued.
This is for the whole U.S. stock market.
And the rest was debt,
that they would borrow money for.
So, Stuart Meyers said, you
know, all this idea that stock
markets function to allocate resources, and the share
market means something is really misleading.
So, what he proposed is
what he called the pecking order
theory.
What he meant is, companies
really don't want to issue new
shares, they just don't want to do it.
You know, we own this company, we're not
letting more people in.
So, what they first do is, they just try to
save their own money.
This is Meyer's explanation.
Companies save money, and when they have money, they spend
it on expanding.
And then, that's the highest on the pecking order.
They like that the best.
But if they really need money,
and they can't save enough to
expand, they have a lot of expansion opportunities.
They'll go to a bank and
borrow, or they'll go to an
investment bank and issue bonds.
And then, only if it's really, really important, and they
can't get enough money, they
will go to selling new shares.
So, I don't know if Stuart Meyer has said
that Karl Marx was right, but
he seemed to be saying that
equity issuance wasn't that important.
However, I think that is misleading.
And I'm going to refer,
then, to another article that came
in much later, criticizing Meyer's.
And the article is by Eugene Fama and Kenneth French.
That's at Chicago and Dartmouth, respectively.
They wrote an article in,
I think it was 2004, 2005.
And again, this is the Journal of Financial Economics, 2005.
They said that the problem with Meyer's pecking order theory
is that Meyer's was looking at aggregate data.
And he was looking at
a time period when there was
relatively little issuance of equity.
Now, when Meyer said only 6% of corporate financing comes
from equity issuance, they were talking about net equity.
That's total new purchases, new sales of shares by
companies minus repurchases of shares by companies.
And so, it averaged out to be a low number.
But in fact, as Fama
and French point out, in the
same year that Meyer's study, from
1973 to 82, 67% of U.S.
companies issued new shares each year.
And also, in subsequent years, the percent went up.
From 1993 to 2002, it was 86%.
So, that's the problem.
So, they're all issuing shares.
Just that some are issuing, and some are buying back.
So, I think that we should conclude that companies really
do use equity financing, even big companies.
And the stock market is important for the price
discovery.
I just wanted to remind you of the term
dilution.
Dilution refers to what happens when a company issues more
shares.
So, imagine that you are showing up at a shareholders
meeting, and someone's saying, well,
the board has decided to
issue, let's say our company has a million shares
outstanding.
They've decided to issue another million, OK, at $10 a
share.
And so, what do you think about that?
Well, if the company had a
million shares, and I owned a
thousand shares, then I owned one thousandth of the company,
right?
If they issue another million
shares, then there would be two
million shares, and I'll own only one two-thousandth of the
company.
So, my first thought is, I don't like that.
I owned a thousandth of
the company, and now I'm falling
in half.
But they would say, on the other hand, look, we're
selling them for $10 a share,
so the company will have $10
million to invest.
So, even though your fraction of the company has been
diluted, the company is worth more.
Then you have to decide whether
$10 a share is a good
enough price.
Is it worth that?
And so, it's never obvious.
You always have to consider dilution, because anything that
expands the number of shares decreases your
interest in the company.
The opposite of dilution occurs
when the company buys back its
shares, and so that's repurchase of a share by a
company.
So, a company can always do that.
They can decide to go either way.
If they need more money, they
can issue shares, and if they
want to get money back, they can buy back.
If they want to get money
out, they can buy back shares.
And these things are very common.
There's statistics, like what Fama and Trent showed for
equity issuance, which show that repurchases are very
common.
It happens all the time.
That's what makes the stock market so active.
One reason, traditionally, for share repurchase is tax
reasons.
If the company repurchases its own
shares, if a company pays a
dividend, that goes in as income for the shareholders,
and it's taxed.
It used to be taxed at
a higher rate than capital gains, so
there was an additional tax.
But now, it's taxed at a higher rate.
So there was an advantage to share repurchases.
Instead of paying dividends, I should just buy back shares.
And then the shareholders would have a better tax, they
would be taxed at a more advantageous rate.
But now, the tax rate on
dividends and the tax rate on
capital gains is the same.
But still, there's always going
to be complicated tax issues,
and so issues of taxation may still motivate some decisions
about share repurchase.
Right.
And as a shareholder, if the
company wants to send me a
dividend, I say, fine, I've got money.
If the company says, I want
to buy some of your shares back,
you say, fine, I've got money.
I don't care.
And so, if they buy back
5% of all their shares, then the
total number of shares goes down.
My fraction of the company is the same.
And I've got money.
It's the same as getting a dividend.
So, you can be confused by these things.
Dilution and repurchase are neither good nor bad.
It depends on circumstances.
And you have to look at
the business and what's being done
with the money.
I wanted to mention, there's another kind of share called
preferred.
There's two kinds of preferred.
There's the preferred and the preferred.
And the preferred is the shareholder.
There's the shareholder and the stockholder.
I've been talking here about common stock.
Common stock is the real ownership in the company.
In other words, you take all the profits, they're the
ultimate owners of the company.
Nobody is above them in the hierarchy.
And preferred stock pays a, it has a set dividend.
But the contract says that
the dividend is so many dollars
per year.
And the board doesn't have to pay it.
But if they cannot, typically the contract says, they cannot
pay a dividend to the common shareholders until all the
dividends to the preferred shareholders are paid up.
And the preferred shareholders typically don't have a vote.
So, this is it.
So, you could buy preferred stock in some company, and
then you would know exactly what your dividend is.
Usually, they just pay a dividend.
It's like owning a bond.
And it's always the same amount.
So, you're not betting on
the company doing better or worse,
generally.
But if it does badly, you're
going to have to pay a dividend
to the preferred shares.
And if it does badly, you
might lose your dividend for a
while.
If the company goes bankrupt, well, then you're out.
But if the company starts doing well again, they've got
to go back and make up
for all the dividends they missed.
So, preferred shares are safer than common shares, but they
lack the upside potential.
They're not as exciting as common shares.
So, when General Motors got
into a crisis, it was a
very, very bad time.
It was a very, very bad time.
And the government, when it
got into a crisis, the U.S.
government bailed out General Motors.
What they did was to buy preferred shares in General
Motors.
So, the U.S. government was a preferred stockholder in
General Motors.
Why did the U.S. government do that?
Why did they buy preferred shares rather than common?
Well, they now do have common shares as well.
I think the government wanted to
not be a stockholder, not to
be a voter in G.E.T.
They wanted to keep their distance, because this is
America, a capitalist country.
If the U.S. bought common shares in General Motors, it's
like nationalizing the company, right?
The government would be on the board.
They would have the votes.
They just didn't want to go that far.
So, they bought preferred shares in General Motors.
Later, General Motors got on
its feet again and bought back
the government's preferred shares.
So, the government is no longer a preferred stockholder.
They're no longer a preferred shareholder in General Motors.
Common is much more important than preferred.
Okay.
Now, I'm going to talk a little bit about dividends.
What determines whether a firm pays dividends?
There's a famous article by John Lintner.
He was a professor at the Harvard Business School, and
also one of the inventors
of the capital asset pricing model.
He wrote an article in, when was
it, it was a long time ago,
about why firms pay dividends.
Remember, it's a judgment call by the board of directors.
So, he wrote an article.
He was a professor at the Harvard Business School.
So, he interviewed people who
were involved in those judgments
and asked them, why do you pay dividends?
Why did you decide to pay
a dividend of a certain amount?
And he wrote a long article
about this, and he found out
that it was impossible to summarize everything they said.
They said so many different things.
Corporations are very complex, and
there's a lot of different
people who have different feelings, and
we're trying to keep people happy.
You want the company to
do well and be perceived well.
So, you know, one thing
he learned is that companies like,
they think that that's our job is to pay dividends.
But when we're young, just like you
don't have to earn an income now,
you're young, right?
Eventually, you know, people are going
to get fed up with you
if you don't earn an income.
So, it's the same thing.
As a company matures, it's part of life's passage,
you start paying dividends, and you
take pride that you're paying dividends
and people are getting money out of you.
He heard a lot of generosity.
He heard a lot of generalities like that.
But what really decides, and one
thing he learned from them is,
they told him, you know, one thing we
don't ever want to do is cut our dividends.
Once we start paying a dividend, if we
stop, it'll get a lot of attention, right?
Well, it's like, for you, right?
You're young people, you don't
have a job, nobody's complaining.
You could go for a while
like this and say you're still young,
but once you start in
a job, and then you quit,
you become a, looks bad, right?
If you're 40 years old and
you say, I'm just dropping out.
Looks worse than if you do it at your age.
It's the same for companies.
Once they start paying a dividend,
they've got to keep paying it.
Otherwise, people get angry.
So, that was one theme.
But, like, Lentner said, even
that doesn't tell the whole story.
So, he tried to build a mathematical model of dividends.
And the model that he came up
with, which he then fit to the data,
and found that it worked very well,
was that these boards of directors have
a target payout ratio of earnings, basically.
This is the bottom line.
That they think they should pay
out a certain fraction of their earnings,
because the shareholders will get mad
if we're making a lot of money,
and we're not sharing it with you.
So, maybe we'll pay out half of our earnings,
and the other half we'll keep as retained earnings,
so that we don't have to go
out and issue new equity or borrow money.
It all sounds reasonable.
And then, because they don't like to cut a dividend,
they don't want to adjust upward quickly.
If earnings shoot up, because if
they go up and raise their dividend,
then they might have to cut
it if earnings go back down.
So, this is the Lentner model.
And it is that the dividends
at time t, year t, let's say,
minus dividends at year t minus 1,
equals rho,
times a number tau, that's the Greek letter tau,
times earnings per share,
minus dividend per share,
at time t minus 1,
plus noise.
So, and tau is between 0 and 1.
So, they have some fraction of
earnings that they want to pay out.
And if earnings per share rise above,
rise so that tau times earnings
per share is greater than dividends,
then they increase their dividends.
And rho is between 0 and 1.
That's the Lentner model.
And he showed with the data that
it pretty much summarizes what firms are doing.
So, they have a payout ratio out of earnings.
They think that, and the payout ratio
has been declining over the last century.
It used to be typically 60, 70%.
In 1900, shareholders were impatient with comfort.
They wanted to see the money.
But they let them keep 30 to 40%.
But now, you know, we become more
and more believers in the stock market,
and we allow companies to do better things.
So, I said I would talk about some examples.
So, let me, examples of specific companies.
Let me get back to my slides here.
I wanted to start with Xerox.
Xerox Corporation.
You've heard of it?
You've heard of Xerox?
It's still there. It exists.
Xerox Corporation was founded in 1906.
It wasn't called Xerox.
It was called the Halloyd Photographic Company.
And they produced photographic equipment.
But they had a big impetus forward
when they met,
Chester Carlson,
who was an inventor.
And what Chester Carlson invented
was a copying machine
that used plain paper.
They used to have copying machines
going all the way back to 1906,
but they were very expensive.
It would cost you, to get a copy of something,
a photographic copy, it cost you
maybe a dollar a page.
Extremely expensive for that time.
But what Carlson invented was a dry copier.
It used to be that
what they had to do was
take a photograph of the document
that you wanted a copy of,
and then process it through the different
chemicals that they use.
It comes out wet and
you have to hang it out.
That was expensive and inconvenient.
But they did have copying machines.
It just didn't work very well.
But he invented this process that,
you could take any paper and put it through,
plain paper, and it would come out hot and dry,
and cheap.
So Xerox became an overnight success,
because they had a patent on Carlson's thing.
And it became the glamour company
of the 1960s and 1970s.
So it was one of the nifty-fifty.
People were very impressed with it.
People were very impressed with Xerox in its day.
So Xerox means dry in Greek.
It's a dry copier.
And it was considered a high-tech company,
moving forward rapidly.
But then it suffered a problem.
Do you know what the problem was?
It was doing really well until sometime in the 1990s,
when another invention came.
And it wasn't Xerox's.
It was called digital copying machines.
Where they would scan in,
the machine would have like a computer
that would scan in the document,
and then produce a copy.
And it had a lot
of advantages over the Xerox copier.
So the company almost went under.
So I have, what I
got here is the balance sheet
from Xerox company.
And this comes from a website, sec.gov.
And I got this from the 10Q report.
And it says,
Xerox is a public company, not a private company.
It's traded on stock exchanges.
So U.S. law says,
any public company must file a quarterly report
with the Securities and Exchange Commission.
And they put it up on their website.
This is the website.
So any public company's balance sheet is on the web.
And it's there, updated every three months.
And I've got a couple of them here.
I've got 1999 and 2010.
In my little company, Case-Shiller Weiss,
Incorporated, it was not public.
So our balance sheet was
never up there on the sec.gov.
That's one of the disadvantages, many people say,
of becoming public.
If you start out as a private company,
then you want to get listed on the stock exchange.
That's called going public.
When you go public, the SEC is on your back.
And you say,
I'm going to file a quarterly report.
You now have to file those quarterly balance sheets.
So this is what I've got.
So this is Xerox.
And it's all up there on sec.gov.
And I've got it for 1999.
This was right at the time
when they were really in trouble,
because the digital revolution was killing Xerox.
And I just wanted to show
a balance sheet of a company,
because there's two sides to the balance sheet.
One is assets and liabilities.
Assets are things the company owns.
Liabilities are debts the company has.
So this is one side of the balance sheet.
But I've got it for two years.
And everything is in millions.
So Xerox had $126 million in cash in 1999.
And they picked up.
They,
the company was dying in 1999.
In 2001, they hired a new CEO, Ann Mulcahy.
And she is credited with saving Xerox,
turning the company around.
So by 2010, at least in terms of cash,
they are doing better.
But maybe not a lot better.
She saved it from extinction.
But she didn't save it,
didn't move it back onto the nifty-fifty.
So I just wanted to
look at what a company owns.
And this is just an example of a balance sheet.
So Xerox owned $15 billion of receivables in 1999.
It was a much lower number in 2010.
I don't know, it might reflect
time of the year or something.
Receivables is money that's owed to them, right?
They ship their copying machine to someone.
The guy says, I'll pay you in three months.
That's a receivable.
And they had inventory.
And they had inventories.
That means probably copying machines ready to be sent out.
And they own buildings.
The building was, I think it went down under Mulcahy.
It went down from $2.4 billion to $1.6 billion.
And then there's a lot of other things.
So the value of everything that the company owns
wasn't much changed.
$28.8 billion.
It went up to $30 billion.
So at least she stopped the company from failing.
But now that's only half of the balance sheet.
I have to go to the other half.
And these are the liabilities.
This is what the company owns.
What it owes.
So it has short-term debt.
Let's talk about 2010.
$1.6 billion.
Long-term debt of $7.8 billion.
Deferred taxes.
They have to pay the taxes.
They have to pay the large
taxes that they know they have
to pay that they haven't paid to.
They didn't have any in 2010.
And preferred stock.
They did have a small amount of preferred stock outstanding,
which counts as a liability.
All right.
And then other liabilities.
I put them all into one category.
Now, OK, this last liability is unique, because it's the
shareholder's equity.
So, what they did, this number, the total liabilities
has to equal the total assets.
This is the same number that
I showed you on the preceding
page.
What's the difference?
It's the shareholder's equity.
OK, so it's $11.9 billion in 2010.
Up from $4.9 billion.
So, by this measure, it's a success.
Now, why is shareholder's equity?
No, it's the value of the company on the books.
So, according to their books, I'll
go back to the, they have
all these assets, right, including buildings and
equipment.
Where did they come up with this number?
How do they know what their buildings and equipment are
worth?
It's an estimate, OK, because
who knows what they could sell
them for?
So, in principle, this shareholder's equity is what
the shares are worth.
All of the shares.
$11.9 billion.
Because if you bought the
company, and you sold all the
assets, and paid off all
the debts, that's what would be
left.
So, you divide that by the
number of shares, and you can
get an estimate of the value of a share.
But I say an estimate, it's
not the same as the market value.
In 2010, there were 1.4 billion shares outstanding in Xerox.
The price per share of a Xerox was $1.9 billion.
So, the share of a Xerox
common share in 2010 was $11.80.
So, if I multiply the number
of shares by the price per share,
the market cap for Xerox is $16.4 billion.
Compare that with the shareholder's equity of $11.9
billion.
So, the company is worth more than its shareholder's equity.
And you might ask, why would that be?
OK.
Well, I think the answer
is, you wouldn't buy this company
to shut it down, right?
You could buy the company for
$16 billion, and then shut it
down, sell off all the assets,
pay off all the debts, and
you'd have $11 billion.
So, that's a sign of Ann Mulcahy's success.
Her company is not going to be shut down.
If the stock price falls
below the shareholder's equity, then,
it becomes at risk for being shut down.
Somebody buys the company and
shuts it down, because I can
make money.
If the company were selling for
$5 billion, I might do that.
Well, not me.
Somebody who arranges these things could do that.
So, I buy the company for $5 billion.
I tell everybody, you're all fired.
We're going out of business.
I sell it.
I get $11.9 billion.
I've doubled my money.
All right?
So, that's the way it is.
Now, a company can sell for less than the shareholder's
equity, because the shareholder's equity is kind
of a funny number.
It's also called stockholder's equity by some people.
Same thing.
It's a funny number, because it involves all kinds of
estimates.
And you really try to sell
that real estate for what it
says here, you might find problems.
So, the value, the market
cap can fall below, the market
capitalization can fall below shareholder's equity.
But probably not too far below.
And this is what worries boards and CEOs.
They watch their stock price
every day, and they've got in
their mind that shareholder's equity.
And if the stock is
falling below that, then they're in
danger of liquidation.
So, they worry.
And that's why every morning, if
you are a CEO, you don't
realize it, if you're a CEO
of a public company, you will be
watching your market cap every day and comparing that with
shareholder's equity.
So, Xerox is an example of
a company that's doing all right
now.
I'll show you its price.
I don't have it all the
way back to 1906, but this is
Xerox price per share.
And it's corrected for splits and other special factors from
1977 to 2001.
And you can see the
incredible crash they took after digital
copying came in.
They were in the middle of the world.
And in the 1990s, they were soaring.
They looked great.
They must have been doing something right.
But they had their heyday, and it's over.
So, Ann Mulcahy came in when the company was utterly
collapsing.
And I guess she's a
success, because it's not its former
self.
It's limping along.
I want to tell you now about Microsoft.
So, that was founded in 1975.
By two people your age, I guess.
And as of 2000, it had assets totaling $52 billion.
And in the last 10 years, it's almost doubled it.
So, its assets are $92 billion.
What does it own?
Well, it has cash of about $4 or $5 billion.
Short-term investments.
A lot of short-term investments.
$37 billion of short-term investments.
This is a company that's doing well.
It's not on the end of its life.
And it has property.
They have this nice campus in Redmond, Washington.
They call it a campus.
It's fun.
Fun place.
Anyway, it's not that expensive.
It's not that expensive.
It's just that they have a lot of real estate.
All their real estate now is only about $8 billion.
And that's all of their computers and equipment.
And then, they own stock.
They don't just own, you
know, this is really different from,
Xerox doesn't own any stock.
They're trying to limp by.
They're trying to get back in stride.
Maybe they have gotten back in stride.
But they've got $10 billion in the stock market.
And this is a company that
didn't pay a dividend until recently.
And it's, you know, Bill Gates and
Paul Allen were still there running it.
And maybe there's a little bit
of truth in this pecking order model.
They just wanted to save their own money.
And they thought their shareholders would
understand that Microsoft is doing so well.
Are you really expecting us to pay your dividend out?
We have all these opportunities.
So, we'll keep the money.
And people had enough faith in
these guys to let them do it.
So, by this account, the total
assets of the company were $92 billion.
But we have to look at liabilities.
Remember, the shareholders'
equity subtracts off liabilities.
So, here are their liabilities.
They have some income taxes that have to be paid.
But this is just, it's only a billion dollars.
That's like small change, right?
It's because of some timing effects.
Accounts payable.
This is a small change.
This is some money that they owe.
They do owe money, because every company delays
paying their bills for a little while, anyway.
So, they have something.
Unearned revenue is revenue that they,
typical cases, they've sold a Windows system.
They've got the money.
But they really haven't completely earned it yet,
because you're going to be calling up with complaints.
They're going to have to do things in
the future for the revenue that they've already earned.
So, they count that as a liability.
They didn't have any debt in 2000.
This is strange, right?
I think they were making so much money.
Why should they borrow?
For some reason, it's now up to about
$10 billion, according to, I can't explain that.
And so, all right.
You add all these up
and subtract them from $92 billion.
And their shareholders' equity is $48 billion.
So, they're doing pretty well.
They're much bigger.
Is that the way to measure Microsoft?
Okay.
This is a measure of the value of Microsoft.
It's really the liquidation value of Microsoft.
So, you could imagine buying Microsoft and then
selling all those assets, shutting it down, firing everybody.
Would that be a smart thing to do?
You fire everybody.
You sell the Redmond campus.
You sell all of their computers.
And what do you end up with?
$48 billion.
Well, let's compare that with the market cap of Microsoft.
They have 8,497,000,000 shares outstanding.
And the price per share at
the end of 2010 was $26.
So, the market cap is $221 billion.
So, that's over five times their shareholders' equity.
That means that they have some other value.
I think I'm running out of time.
This is a plot of –
it's interesting what happens in the world.
This is my last – I'll stop with this.
This is the price per share of Microsoft.
I should disclose, I'm now a shareholder.
I wish I were a shareholder back then.
Nobody believed it.
This only goes back to 86, but
the company – maybe it was private.
I forget when it went public.
So, we don't have prices.
But then we have prices in 86.
It really had a run until 2000.
And then something broke with Microsoft as well.
It looks a little bit like Xerox, doesn't it?
I think it was the end of the high-tech bubble.
This was a bubble in tech
prices, and Microsoft rode the bubble.
But it's still doing very well.
It's just not going up lately.
Anyway, this is an example.
We're going to talk about real estate.
The other asset class that I mentioned
is even bigger than the stock market.
And I'll talk about that
in our next lecture on Wednesday.